<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief accompt of the Turks late expedition, against the kingdome of Hungary, Transylvania, and the hereditary countries of the Emperour together with an exact narrative of the remarquable occurrences at the siege of Nevvhausel. Translated out of the Dutch. Printed with privilege.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5957A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212383</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896900</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135483</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135483)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ;  2462:15, 2550:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief accompt of the Turks late expedition, against the kingdome of Hungary, Transylvania, and the hereditary countries of the Emperour together with an exact narrative of the remarquable occurrences at the siege of Nevvhausel. Translated out of the Dutch. Printed with privilege.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22, [2], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Richard Hodgkinson, and Thomas Mab,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXIII. [1663]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>"The continuation of a discourse, lately printed, and entitled A briefe accompt of the Turks late expedition against the kingdome of Hungary, Transylvania; and the hereditary countries of the Emperour. Translated out of Dutch" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous. It was probably also issued separately (Wing C5957A).</note>
                  <note>A reissue of Wing B4522B with the addition of the "Continuation", which was printed about a month later (see D2r).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1661-1664 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  History --  Turkish occupation, 1526-1699 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Transylvania (Romania) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Nové Zámky (Czechoslovakia) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135483:1"/>
            <p>THE CONTINUATION OF A DISCOURSE, Lately Printed, and Entitled A Briefe Accompt of the TURKS late Expedition againſt the Kingdome of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary, Tranſylvania;</hi> and the Hereditary Countries of the Emperour.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Hodgkinſon,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Mab,</hi> MDCLXIII.</p>
            <p>WITH PRIVILEGE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135483:2"/>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:135483:2"/>
            <head>To the READER,</head>
            <p>HAving about a Month ſince, Printed a ſmall Relation in Three Sheets of Paper concerning the <hi>Turks</hi> late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in <hi>Hungary, Tranſylvania, &amp;c.</hi> with good Acceptance: I thought I could not better Gratify their Curioſity, that took the Peyns to read the Former, then by Seconding That Introduction, with This <hi>Continuation</hi> of the Story: being Turned out of <hi>Dutch,</hi> and the Work of the Same Originall <hi>Author,</hi> beginning with This where the Other brake off.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <head>A Continuation of the <hi>TURKS</hi> Proceedings, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all This Action the <hi>Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier</hi> has playd both the <hi>Fox,</hi> and the <hi>Lion,</hi> mingling <hi>Fair words,</hi> and <hi>Threatnings;</hi> and Publiſhing ſtill before the Blow, ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Immunity</hi> to ſuch as would range themſelves under his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, as he well knew moſt likely to work upon the People, he had to deal with. It is true, that theſe Overtures of Clemency, from ſo barbarous an Enemy, were look'd upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135483:3"/>by the wiſer ſort, rather as a trick of <hi>State,</hi> then <hi>Good-faith;</hi> yet with the Generality, This way of proceeding took effect.</p>
            <p>The Place moſt in the <hi>Turks</hi> eye was <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> being the chief City of the <hi>Nether-Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary:</hi> (wherein is laid up the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Crown) A Place, conſiderable both for the <hi>Goodlineſs</hi> of the Town, and for the <hi>Situation</hi> of it; to which advantage the <hi>Turk</hi> was no Stranger; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the frequent <hi>Alarms,</hi> he gave to that City, the gaining whereof, would have open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a way to <hi>Vienna,</hi> on the One ſide, and to <hi>Raab, Comorra,</hi> and <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> on the Other: The <hi>Danube</hi> paſsing by in Two Branches, to the Iſland <hi>Schut,</hi> at the end whereof ſtands the Fort <hi>Comorra;</hi> and <hi>Raab</hi> not far off. Nor was it unknown to <hi>Count Strozzi,</hi> (the Governour of <hi>Presburg</hi>) how much the ſafety of the <hi>Whole,</hi> Depended upon the Security of This <hi>Part,</hi> which mov'd him to make timely proviſion, for the Defence thereof. But the neighbouring Places, that lay open, as <hi>St. George, Poſing, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern,</hi> &amp;c. choſe rather to ſubmit, then expoſe themſelves to the extremityes of Fire and Sword, by an unprofitable Oppoſition. <hi>Neutra</hi> indeed (a Place not far from <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> nor leſs defenſible) might have reſiſted, but did not, and upon the Rendition the Garriſon,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135483:3"/>according to agreement, was conducted to <hi>Presburg. Tyrnaw,</hi> and other Towns yielded alſo.</p>
            <p>The Enemies next Attempt was upon <hi>Schin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> wherein was lodg'd a fayr Artillery, but the Governour deported himſelf valiantly, and beat them off. By this time, <hi>October</hi> was half over, and the ſeaſon, call'd the <hi>Turk</hi> to his <hi>Winter-Quarters:</hi> who finding his time loſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Schinta,</hi> drew off to <hi>Newhauſel;</hi> which place is now repaired, and ſtrongly Garriſon'd, the River <hi>Neutra</hi> being brought round about it. From Thence, the <hi>Turk</hi> took his march, with a conſiderable Body, to the <hi>Ship-Bridge</hi> at <hi>Gran,</hi> and cauſed ſome of his great Guns to be paſſ'd over there, as if his purpoſe had been to Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his own Territories. Thoſe of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauſel</hi> laboured hard to get into the <hi>Schut,</hi> and ſettle themſelves, betwixt the Two Forts of <hi>Raab,</hi> and <hi>Comorra:</hi> whereupon <hi>Montecuculi</hi> and <hi>Serini</hi> joyn'd their Forces to oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>And now the fortune of the Warre ſeem'd a little to flatter the <hi>Chriſtians; Nicholas Serini</hi> on the 17. of <hi>Oct.</hi> defeating a Party of 300 <hi>Turks,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Peter,</hi> about the ſame time fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon a Body of about 7000 of them near <hi>Carlſtadt,</hi> on the Frontiers of <hi>Stiria:</hi> where they deſigned an Inrode upon the <hi>Christians;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135483:4"/>but <hi>Count Serini,</hi> and <hi>Count Aursburg,</hi> from an <hi>Ambuſcade,</hi> brake in among them, ſlew 1000, and took 100 Priſoners; among which were diverſe Perſons of Note, and the Son of a great <hi>Baſſa:</hi> the reſt diſperſt themſelves; and the Victorious in this Adventure got great Booty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Serinies</hi> have ſhew'd themſelves, in This their deportment, the true Heirs of the Honour, and Valour of that Noble Family; and they put us in mind, of a memorable Action, which was performed by their Grandfather, <hi>Nicholas Serini</hi> in the year 1566, <hi>To his Eternall Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="italic">On the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt 1566, Solyman</hi> the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent</hi> layd Siege to the Fort <hi>Sigeth,</hi> wherein this great Captain, <hi>Nicholas Serini</hi> was Governour; who made many bold Sallyes upon the Eenemy, took many Priſoners, and at one time cauſed <hi>300 Turks</hi> to be beheaded; which ſo far enraged <hi>Solyman,</hi> that he plyed his Batteries, and Attempts, with greater fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then before. <hi>Serini</hi> perceiving the <hi>New-Town</hi> to be upon the poynt of being entred, cauſed it to be ſet on fire, and retreated into the <hi>Old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="italic">A while after, the <hi>Turks</hi> aſſaulted the <hi>Old Town,</hi> but were ſo bravely received, that in One Storm they loſt <hi>2000</hi> men. However they attempted it again, and carried it; whereupon, <hi>Serini</hi> was forced to retire into the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> against which the Enemy planted a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135483:4"/>Battery, and gave One ſurious Attaque; but were beaten off with great loſs.</p>
            <p rend="italic">While This paſſ'd, <hi>Solyman</hi> died of a Bloody-Flux, <hi>(Sept. 4.)</hi> but <hi>Mahomet Baſſa</hi> labouring as much as poſsible to keep his death conceal'd from the <hi>Turks,</hi> cauſed the Corps (Embalmed, and Gloriouſly Clothed) to be expoſ'd in a dark place to the People, as ſitting on his Throne, and the <hi>Baſſa</hi> himſelf, with all his uſuall Ceremonyes, and Reverence, feigning ſome ſingular matter of privacy, and buſineſs with him. At length, the <hi>Baſſa</hi> went out of the Tent, wiping his eyes as if he had been crying; which gave the Officers occaſion to enquire, why he wept? To whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that <hi>It grieved his heart to think how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brave Souldiers would be ſuddenly put to the Sword:</hi> for (ſayes he) <hi>Solyman</hi> has made a <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>deſperate Oath,</hi> that if this Place be not taken in two dayes, every Colonel that bears any Charge in the Attempt, ſhall certainly be put to death. Hereupon, the <hi>Janizaryes</hi> fell into a direct Rage, and gave a furious Aſſault, but were repulſed with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding loſſe: they had howover ſet fire to the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> and now the Noble Defender of it, ſeeing his fate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, call'd the ſmall remainder of his men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, and exhorted them to ſtand by him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to dye with him. Whereupon, he Clothed himſelf in a <hi>Violet-coloured Velvet Suit,</hi> took the <hi>Key</hi> of the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> and ſome Gold in his <hi>Pocket;</hi> cauſ'd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135483:5"/>the Gates to be open'd, and the great Guns to be drawn thither, and diſcharged among the Enemy: and in a Cloud of Smoak, he iſſued forth with his Men, among the <hi>Turks,</hi> and fought till he was ſhot in the head. This was the end of the Valiant <hi>Serini.</hi> It was rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned that <hi>20000 Turks</hi> were ſlain before this Fort. No ſooner was <hi>Serini</hi> fain, but the <hi>Infidels</hi> throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Corps, cut off his head, and ſet it on a Pole for one day, after which, they ſent it with a Scoffe to <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour. <hi>Now to reſume the Story.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Hollach,</hi> being choſen General of the <hi>Imperiall Auxiliaryes,</hi> came to <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> his Forces (amounting to 6 or 7000 men) being Enquarter'd betwixt <hi>That,</hi> and <hi>Crembs;</hi> The Emperours Army, lying at that time near <hi>Presburg,</hi> to recruit, being much weakned by many Inconveniencies. The whole Army, (with the <hi>Hungartans, Croatians,</hi> and <hi>Auxiliaryes,</hi> was computed to be 40000 ſtrong; but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall heads, of ſo many Nations, who at this time were almoſt all in <hi>Vienna,</hi> could not (it ſeems) agree ſo well together, as not to need his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Majeſtie's ſingular Care, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect on to keep them from flying into <hi>Partyes,</hi> and <hi>Paſsions.</hi> There was an Intent to joyn 7 or 8000 men that were rayſed in <hi>Sileſia</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:135483:5"/>to This Body; but the <hi>Sileſian</hi> Forces would neither march out of their native Country, nor obey any Forreign Command; ſo that They ſtayd at home to defend their <hi>Borders,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the Paſſage by <hi>Jablunka.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were laying their heads, and their Forces together, to put themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Poſture, the Enemy brake up with his main Body before <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> and about the end of <hi>October,</hi> took his March toward <hi>Gran,</hi> and <hi>Offen.</hi> The <hi>Tartars</hi> alſo with their Prey marched toward <hi>Tartary,</hi> carrying along with them their chiefeſt Captives in Coaches, and Wagons, driving their ordinary Priſoners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with Whips, naked; and their hair flying about their eyes, juſt like ſo many Beaſts. In <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Hungary,</hi> they met with ſome oppoſition, at which time many of the Captives were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of their hands, and about 2000 of theſe <hi>Tartars</hi> put to the Sword. Count <hi>Nicholas Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini</hi>'s Deſigne, was to fall upon them, at their paſſing over the <hi>Ship-Bridge,</hi> and followed them cloſe, ſometime in the <hi>Rear,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wile on the <hi>Flanck,</hi> ſtill obſerving their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion till he found his opportunity to attaque them.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:135483:6"/>
            <p>Upon the laſt day of <hi>October,</hi> he ſet upon the <hi>Rear,</hi> and took from them 5 Wagons full of Captives, that they had gotten in <hi>Moravia;</hi> 200 Oxen, and 40 Wagons with Proviſion. In this Action, he did not only releaſe the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, but defeated alſo their Drivers, which were about 600 <hi>Janizaries.</hi> They fought ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for 2 hours from behind their Wagons, ſo that Count <hi>Serini</hi> his <hi>Huſſars,</hi> were forced to quit their Horſes, and fight them on foot: which they did with excellent conduct, and ſucceſſe, giving Quarter only to Two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Note, whoſe lives were at their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
            <p>Herewith, this <hi>Campagnia</hi> ſeem'd to be at an end, and Count <hi>Serini,</hi> having in appearance little to do further with the Enemy, let his men march homeward: (wanting Fodder for their Horſes) the Enemy in the mean while ſteering their Courſe toward <hi>Gran, Offen,</hi> and <hi>Weiſſenburg,</hi> as to their <hi>Winter-Quarters.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> left a Garriſon of 4000 in <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Two <hi>Baſſaes;</hi> and 10000 about the Fort, partly to defend the <hi>Place,</hi> and partly to repair the <hi>Fortifications.</hi> In <hi>Neutra,</hi> the Enemy left 1500 men, which Place was plundred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135483:6"/>the Army march'd away. The Earls <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> and <hi>Tekelly,</hi> with a Body of near 15000 men rayſed in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper</hi> and <hi>Nether-Hungary,</hi> came In to Count <hi>Serini;</hi> which Conjunction the <hi>Turks</hi> mightily endeavoured to hinder, but could not effect it. Theſe Forces are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe drawn out of the Field, ſince that time.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Auxiliaryes,</hi> That is to ſay; the <hi>Heſſen, Brunſwick, Lunenburg, Munſter</hi> Forces; and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the <hi>Rhyne</hi> (ſome of which, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoſe from <hi>Heſſen Darmſtadt</hi> periſh'd upon the <hi>Danube</hi>) are put into <hi>Winter-Quarters</hi> on the ſide of that River; but the <hi>Saxon,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg Auxiliaryes,</hi> are to lye in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Moravia;</hi> and the <hi>Sileſian</hi> Forces to tarry in their own Country: for the Councel of Warre at <hi>Vienna,</hi> did not hold it Adviſable, to Quarter all the <hi>Auxiliaryes</hi> near together, for fear of Surfeits upon the Fruits, beſide that they would have wanted Fodder for their Horſe, and in the foul deep wayes they would have found great trouble to have fetch'd it. Another Conſideration was, the Eaſing of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who were already ſufficiently weary of Billeting Souldiers. In Fine; there
<pb facs="tcp:135483:7"/>is no great Noyſe of Armes, and Action, at preſent, but how the Enemy may be oppoſ'd next Spring, is the Conſulation, and the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; who threatens <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the <hi>Empire,</hi> with no leſſe then 3 or 400000 Men at the Next <hi>Campagnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was now Reſolv'd by his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Majeſty, to go to <hi>Regenſpurg</hi> about the end of <hi>November</hi> following; there to Adviſe about the Relieſe of the <hi>Empire,</hi> and indeed of <hi>Christendome:</hi> and his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Majeſty did likewiſe Reſolve to ſend Embaſſadours to the <hi>Pope, Spain, France,</hi> &amp;c. to Sollicit Succour. From the <hi>Pope, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes</hi> are expected, <hi>France</hi> proffers <hi>Men</hi> (but who dares receive them?) <hi>Swede</hi> is willing to Aſsiſt in reſpect of their Intereſt in <hi>Germany,</hi> and they have ſent already 700 well mounted that came from <hi>Bremen:</hi> ſo that the Inſtant Buſineſs of the <hi>Empire</hi> ſeems to be rather <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> then <hi>Preſent Defence;</hi> and to look for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward toward the Spring: the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already diſperſ'd his Letters of Menace, and Defyance to all <hi>Christendome</hi> throughout the <hi>Emperours</hi> Hereditary Countries.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>Turks</hi> withdrawing the Groſſe of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135483:7"/>his Army, from about <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> over the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube,</hi> with a Countenance of Diſpoſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his <hi>Winter-Quarter;</hi> Mens minds began to be a little Compoſ'd and Quiet; till <hi>Abaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> the <hi>Grand Signiors</hi> Creature in <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> undertook the <hi>Turks</hi> Aftergame, with thoſe Forces that ſtay'd behind; labouring his Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to poſſeſſe himſelf of the <hi>Berg,</hi> or <hi>Mine-Towns,</hi> (whence comes the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Gold) and other Frontier Places, and Houſes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Right to his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Majeſty: which Perfidious Deſigne the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Army could not conveniently either prevent, or oppoſe, being already diſperſ'd for want of Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes both for Man, and Beaſt.</p>
            <p>This ſame <hi>Abafti;</hi> paſſ'd in Common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, for a Perſon well-affected to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and as One that wayted only a fayre Opportunity to draw his Sword againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> but his Actions have now diſcover'd him: for perceiving what Reputation, Preſents, and other Popular Advantages, have accrued to the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> and the Chiefe Officers of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, upon the Gayning of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel;</hi> he likewiſe turn'd his Study, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours the ſame way, not doubting by his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135483:8"/>Intereſts, and Services, to draw from the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Emperour</hi> as fayre a Reward; undertaking not only to keep, what was already gotten, but to Enlarge the Conqueſt by a Confiderable Addition.</p>
            <p>It being found neither commodious, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to expoſe the <hi>Turks,</hi> and other <hi>Aſiatick,</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Forces, (whoſe Bodyes have been uſed to a Temperate warme Ayre) to the cold Winter-Blaſts of <hi>Hungary:</hi> (which are ſharp, though not long) the Hardſhip of the <hi>Winter-Warre</hi> was rather committed to the <hi>Mountaineers;</hi> That is; to the <hi>Abaftiſh Tranſylvanians, Moldavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Wallachians,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe Part it is, to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn the <hi>Turks</hi> Ground at leaſt, if not carry the Victory further; and in Briefe, to hold the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> in Play, till the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, may conveniently take the Field again toward the Spring. And leaſt the Town <hi>Neutra</hi> ſhould be left Naked; inſtead of about 600 <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Janyzaryes,</hi> that were taken out of That Garriſon, Others, that could better endure the Ayre of the Place, were put in, and a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of 115 <hi>Janizaryes</hi> into the Caſtle, (a Sort of People which are of great Credit with the <hi>Turk</hi> in Martiall Affayrs; and in truth, Theſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135483:8"/>were the Men that ventur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d the hardeſt before <hi>Newhauſel.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Janizaryes</hi> are <hi>Chriſtians Children,</hi> which were either taken <hi>Captive,</hi> or given in the way of <hi>Tribute,</hi> by ſuch <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as have done Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the <hi>Turks,</hi> Theſe Children are trayn'd up from their Childhood, in the <hi>Mahumetan Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> and Inur'd to <hi>Military</hi> exerciſes. They are very Numerous and Valiant; and doubtleſs the beſt ſupport of the <hi>Turkiſh Empire.</hi> As their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of great uſe, and ſervice to the <hi>Ottoman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> in ſome caſes, ſo is it in others not leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, their Revolts and Tumults being ſeldom Iaid, or quieted without Horrible Rapine, and Effuſion of Blood. Miſery of Miſeryes! that the Children of <hi>Christians</hi> ſhould be thus engaged in ſo Implacable an Enmity to the Dictates both of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Nature!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About This Time; Newes was brought that a young Son was born to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> upon which Tydings, ſuch a face was ſet upon the Buſyneſs, as if it had been a Material Part of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to welcome this young Idoll into the world with the Sacrifice of more <hi>Christian</hi>-Bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abafti</hi>'s Ayme, (as we have ſaid before) was to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135483:9"/>work himſelf in among the <hi>Mine-Towns.</hi> The two firſt conſiderable Blocks in his way were <hi>Lewents,</hi> and <hi>Novigrad,</hi> (beſide others of leſs Importance.) In <hi>Lewents</hi> were good Fighting men, Back'd with a Caſtle that was well fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Thick walls, and Firm Turrets. In This Place, the Enemy found ſtout oppoſition, and Loſt many men before it; but at laſt preſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it with greater Numbers and no Relief ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing within diſtance, they took it upon Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. Thoſe that March'd out were in no ſort Injured, and Thoſe that ſtayd behind were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and did Homage.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Lewents</hi> followed <hi>Novigrad,</hi> that lyes deeper in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Hungary;</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a ſtrong Place, and environ'd with a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſe;</hi> yet after a ſtout Reſiſtance was forc'd to Render to the Enemy. The Forces in it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to <hi>Waitzen,</hi> where they betook themſelves to work for their Living, as the Reſt of the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, and are enjoyn'd to be ever in Readyneſs with their Armes. The Governour of it, by Name, <hi>Pedami,</hi> got leave from <hi>Abafti</hi> to go to his Countrey-Houſe in <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> and to dwell there, which ſoon after he did.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:135483:9"/>
            <p>On the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſide, there was no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will wanting toward the Relief of any of theſe Places; but all their Attempts fell ſhort, by reaſon of many Fatalities, and Accidents Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſucceſſes encouraged the Enemy to draw nearer to the <hi>Mine-Towns,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the making of their <hi>Winter-Quarter</hi> thereabouts, and in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Hungary.</hi> A Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour was then diſperſed that the <hi>Great Vizier</hi> had Commanded the Magiſtrates of <hi>Fryſtadt,</hi> and the Neighbouring Parts, upon pain of death to make a <hi>Ship-bridge</hi> over the <hi>Waegh</hi> with all ſpeed, and to provide Victuals and Fodder to entertain him at his comming back. Thus did new Cares and Troubles come on, in a ſeaſon, when every man flatter'd himſelf with ſome hopes of Reſpit and Repoſe.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Serini,</hi> that till now, ſtaid in the Iſle of <hi>Schutt.</hi> put himſelf Inſtantly into Motion, and now and then, met with ſome Parties, and took good Booty from them; but alaſs? This would not ſerve to ſet the Ballance even. Upon <hi>November</hi> 12. He took, in a Mooriſh Place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Raab,</hi> and <hi>Comorra,</hi> ten Camels and as many Mules, laden with Truneks full of Gold and Silver-plate; together with the Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, who were bound for <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with this Booty.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:135483:10"/>
            <p>In <hi>Comorra</hi> (where the Officers were at that time under Queſtion, and came off well, about the Surrender of <hi>Newhauſel</hi>) there were great Complaints of Scarcity of Proviſion; the Country being ſo miſerably waſted round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. Whereupon, at <hi>Vienna</hi> it was taken into thought, how thoſe out-lying Garriſons might be ſupplyed, and the Enemy diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of their aime, who knew full well the State of their Neceſſities. It is certain, that the <hi>Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliaries</hi> and other Forces that were Quarter'd in <hi>Comorra,</hi> would much rather have kept the field, if all other Circumſtances would have permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it; but thoſe <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> who by too liberal Feeding on the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> and <hi>Moravian</hi> Fruits, had contracted diſeaſes, neither could, nor would ſtir; beſide that their General, Count <hi>Hohenlo,</hi> a Prudent, Expert, and Judicious Commander, gave many weighty Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. No ſooner had this Lord made an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance in <hi>Vienna;</hi> but ill Fortune met with him his Chamber being Robb'd of VVritings, Moneys, and Jewels, to the value of betwixt twenty and thirty thouſand; <hi>Rix Dollars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Swediſh Auxiliaries</hi> were not yet come up; but by Advice from <hi>Leipſick,</hi> they were then upon their March not far from <hi>Thuringen,</hi> (about the midſt of <hi>November</hi>) and 150. horſe were likewiſe to come from <hi>Pomerania,</hi> which Forces became the Ground of great Miſtakes,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135483:10"/>happening to be in Motion juſt upon that Nick of time, when the <hi>Erſordians</hi> (being then Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed) were in Expectation of the <hi>Men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ziſh</hi> troups: Upon whom they Iſſued forth, and in their Return left two Carpenters behinde them, whom they hanged upon a VVaggon, which did much enflame the tumult. but the <hi>Swediſh</hi> troups, which had ſo much troubled the heads of divers People, proved to be a Force of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign, and Quality.</p>
            <p>The Rumour of the Return of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, (now ſo late in <hi>November</hi>) Encreaſed more and more; at which time <hi>Filleck</hi> (Some ten mile from <hi>Caſſaw</hi>) was given for loſt; So that certain Regiments were immediately ſent to make good the other <hi>Mine-Townes,</hi> which the Enemy had particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in their Eye for a <hi>Winter-Quarter.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> which about this time ranfom'd themſelves from the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſpeak much of the Stupendious Preparations, which are now in hand againſt <hi>Chriſtendome;</hi> Affirming it for a Certainty, that the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> is reſolv'd to take the field next Spring with an Army of three hundred thouſand Men, which cauſes great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities in <hi>Poband, Hungary, Moravia, Sileſia,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia;</hi> but the <hi>Polanders,</hi> being at peace with the <hi>Turks,</hi> conceived themſelves in ſome meaſure ſecured by virtue of that Agreement; but in the <hi>Tartars, Moldavians,</hi> and <hi>Walachians,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:135483:11"/>they have not much confidence: Eſpecially, when they are upon their Excurſions. Many were of opinion, that the <hi>Turks</hi> were forc'd upon an irregular and precipitate retreat for want of Proviſions, and that their attempts ſo late in the year, upon <hi>Moravia,</hi> and the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Provinces,</hi> were cauſed partly by the Inviting plenty of all neceſſaries, which thoſe Countreys afford; and in part, by the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement they received from their Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in thoſe Quarters; beſide the ſcarcity, which their longer continuance, upon the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube</hi> would infallibly have produced therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, to the great inconvenience of their Armyes next Spring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hungary</hi> lay now groaning under the burden of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power, and longing for aid; the <hi>Infidels</hi> over-ſpreading it like a diſmal Cloud, charged with Hail and Thunder: all mens thoughts, being ſollicitous, for deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and in continual expectation where the ſtorme would fall. Many were of opinion that <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> was the beſt expedient in this extremity; but betwixt the ſence of their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance</hi> ſworn to the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and the <hi>diſtruſt</hi> they had of the <hi>Turks</hi> Juſtice to his word, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers held off.</p>
            <p>The Enemy (who did nothing raſhly, though as is generally ſuppoſed, rather acting
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135483:11"/>by <hi>Inſtigation</hi> then <hi>choice</hi>) counted it moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeable to draw toward <hi>Caſſaw</hi> the head City of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-hungary;</hi> knowing full well that when ever the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite,</hi> they would make this place the Seat of Warr, and ſettle themſelves There: VVherefore the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels</hi> went roundly to work, removing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever might hinder their Progreſſe, before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuccour could come up to them, which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour would however at laſt ſignify not much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo Potent an Enemy.</p>
            <p>About this time, the <hi>Polanders</hi> were a little Frighted with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who though return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing homeward with their booty already got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, might yet be tempted by their greedineſs after more, to break into the <hi>Cracovian, Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood-ſhip;</hi> and from thence to advance into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> according to the old ſaying, <hi>Si Turca veniet in Germaniam, Ibit per Poloniam.</hi> If the <hi>Turk</hi> comes into <hi>Germany,</hi> he ſhall paſſe through <hi>Poland.</hi> Theſe Incarnat and Rapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Devils, however kept off yet, and carryed their prey to their <hi>Cavernes</hi> there to divide it. One thing is, that <hi>Cham,</hi> being the head and Sovereign of theſe <hi>Tarters</hi> which had been in <hi>Moravia,</hi> was a friend to <hi>Poland,</hi> and about this time his Forces went in abundance with the King of <hi>Poland</hi> (in perſon) and the Army, together with a great number of <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135483:12"/>the <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> marching over the River <hi>Nieper;</hi> otherwiſe call'd <hi>Boriſthenes.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> however went on in their proceeding, ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Shemnitz, Cremnitz,</hi> and other <hi>Mine-towns,</hi> and ſending threatning Letters to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates thereabout, who being over-aw'd by the Terrour of thoſe Menaces, moved the People under them to do homage to theſe <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi> The taking of the Fort <hi>Novigrad,</hi> (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtrength whereof the People ſo much depended) did not a little conduce to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting of the reſt. And now they made their excurſions toward <hi>Tokay,</hi> (where their Nobleſt Wines grow) a ſtrong Hold, moted round about, &amp; alwayes reputed as invincible. Upon this place they practic'd both <hi>ſubtilty</hi> and <hi>force,</hi> as they had done before <hi>Novigrad;</hi> but honeſt men had the keeping of it, and ſo they were forc'd to paſſe it by.</p>
            <p>About this time the <hi>Turks</hi> cauſed the late ſubdued <hi>Lewents</hi> to be demoliſh'd, as not lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner of the Fortification, and ſent a Menacing Order to thoſe of <hi>Fryſtadt,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch out of hand two Bridges over the <hi>Waegh,</hi> larger then the former, and to make them broad enough for whole Squadrons to paſſe a Breaſt; And now they began to talk loud of another Invaſion into <hi>Moravia;</hi> to which end, many thouſands of the <hi>Tawny-Tartars</hi> throng'd
<pb facs="tcp:135483:12"/>into the Camp, as if thoſe of the other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, had not yet playd the devils ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Country; Whereupon to prevent that Inrode, a <hi>Counter-mand</hi> was ſent to moſt of thoſe forces, that were now march'd, or march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off to their <hi>Winter-Quarters;</hi> and Order given them to bend their Courſe toward the <hi>Waegh.</hi> Although this Countenance of the <hi>Turks</hi> deſign gain'd not much Credit, in regard of the ſeaſon of the Year, it was however held for good diſcretion not to be too ſecure.</p>
            <p>Near the end of <hi>November,</hi> came to <hi>Vienna-Baron de Goes</hi> (with leave of the <hi>Great Vizier,</hi> and in company of a <hi>Turkiſh Chiaux</hi> of <hi>Offen</hi>) who long time had been employ'd as the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours</hi> Agent toward the intended Treaty for Peace; which <hi>Baron,</hi> Affirmes that the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> with the <hi>Tartar Cham,</hi> have reſolved, with an Incredible Force, to come perſonally into the Field next Spring; and Joyn the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power againſt <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the taking of which Reſolution, vaſt Quantities of Rice and Corne were Ordered at <hi>Adrinople,</hi> and <hi>Philippopoli</hi> to be carried to <hi>Greek-Weiſſenberg,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Offen.</hi> This determination and Proceeding, engaged the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to uſe their utmoſt Endeavours Poſſible, for the bringing of a conſiderable Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into the Field next Spring; and to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb facs="tcp:135483:13"/>his <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty having firſt given Audience to the Report of the ſaid <hi>Baron,</hi> gives immediate Order for Preparations; taking his Journey to the <hi>Diet</hi> at <hi>Regenſpurg,</hi> to Stirr up the Princes of the <hi>Empire</hi> to a General Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi> In the <hi>Interim,</hi> the Arch-Duke <hi>Charles Joſeph,</hi> being deſign'd to keep his Reſidence in <hi>Vienna,</hi> put himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way thither from <hi>Lintz;</hi> but fell into ſuch a weakneſſe upon the Journey, that he was enforc'd to go back. The Chief Officers appointed to ſtay behinde in <hi>Vienna,</hi> applyed themſelves with all diligence to the putting their Orders in Execution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schinta</hi> was now provided afreſh with Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition and Proviſion, and the Great Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry removed from thence, the <hi>Montecuculiſh</hi> Army, which for a long time had been Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd near the <hi>Presburg Ship-Bridge,</hi> mov'd from thence toward <hi>Moravia.</hi> The Count <hi>de Souches</hi> conceived ſome hopes of recovering <hi>Neutra,</hi> and prepar'd accordingly; the loſs of that place being reputed not much inferiour to the loſs of <hi>New hauſel: Neutra</hi> being an <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Seat, <hi>New-hauſel</hi> only a Seat for <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,</hi> which begat a greater Zeal, and Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs toward the Recovery of the Place.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
